Miguel Xochicale

School of Biomedical Engineering and Imaging Sciences
Department of Biomedical Engineering

King's College London, UK ■ miguel.xochicale@kcl.ac.uk

http://mxochicale.github.io/ mxochicale

Research Interests My research interests are in real-time and automatic Signal and Image Processing techniques in the context of Human-Robot Interaction, Movement Variability, Wearables in Medicine, Ultrasound-Guided Interventions, Medical Robotics, Fetal Biomechanics, and Research Software Engineering. I have passion for real-time AI and biomechanics technologies for Healthcare.

EDUCATION

The University of Birmingham

Birmingham, UK

Ph.D. in Computer Engineering

Nov 2014 - Nov 2018

Thesis: Nonlinear Analysis to Quantify Movement Variability in Human-Humanoid Interaction.

Supervisors: Professor Chris Baber and Professor Martin Russell

Thesis submission: 26/10/2018. Passed Viva: 11/01/2019. Awarded PhD degree: 12/07/2019.

Links: Thesis: ☐ Github: ☐ Website: ☐

Institute of Astrophysics, Optics and Electronics (INAOE)

Puebla, México

M.Sc. in Signal Processing

Sep 2004 – Sep 2006

Thesis: Design of digital filters with fewer multipliers

Supervisor: Dr. Gordana Jovanovic Dolecek

Links: Thesis: 🗷 Github: 🖶

Puebla Institute of Technology

Puebla, México

Aug 1999 – Sep 2004

B.Eng. in Electronics Thesis: Speed control for a two-degrees-of-freedom Robot in LabVIEW.

Supervisor: M.Sc. José Esteban Torres León.

Links: Thesis: 口Github: 🖶

Professional Experience

King's College London Research Associate in Real-time AI Ultrasound Imaging

London UK

Sep 2021 – Present

- PI: Dr. Alberto Gomez
- I am scientifically contributing to automatic biometric recognition of Electrocardiography ultrasound data using real-time deep learning techniques and frameworks with Python-based and Qt programming languages via GitHub. Additionally, I am leading the preparation of one proceeding and one manuscript in the area of medical imaging with real-time deep learning techniques. All previous activities in collaboration with renowned clinicians and engineers in KCL, University of Oxford and University of Melbourne. See more at (2).

King's College London Research Associate in Software and Hardware Engineering

London UK Apr 2019 – Aug 2021

• PI: Prof. Tom Vercauteren

• I pushed forward the state-of-the-art of Ultrasound-Guidance Interventions where was involved in the development of a needle tip tracking system, real-time ultrasound image processing, quality management system (QMS) for clinical translation of medical devices, and public engagement activities. Similarly, I developed validation experiments with linear stages under Windows and GNU/Linux OSs, designed electronic PCBs and design CAD pieces for 3D printing holders, characterised ultrasonic transducers, operate clinical ultrasound devices and contributing to a Python library via GitHub following QMS. All the previous activities in collaboration with an amazing team of renowned clinicians, engineers, QMS specialists and researchers in KCL and UCL. Additionally, I lead the preparation of one manuscript in a high-impact factor journal. See more at (27).

INAOE's Robotics Laboratory Research Assistant in Robotics

Puebla, México Feb 2013 – Aug 2013

• Advisor: Dr. Angélica Muñoz Meléndez

• I developed a Human-Robot Interaction application for dancing activities based on a Patrolbot mobile robot and a single three-axial accelerometer. (See documents and code: 🗹).

Madero University Teaching Lecturer in Mechatronic Engineering

Puebla, México Jan 2012 – Jan 2013

- I proposed and supervised the following students projects: Haptic Referee Glove, Lightmetre and Pychometre Sensors, Smart Irrigation, Persistent Of Vision Bicycle Wheel and a Delta Robot Structure (See documents and code: 🗷).
- I proposed and designed a Mechatronic Laboratory which includes: (i) a benchmark for laboratories in mechatronics in México and Puebla, (ii) a 3D layout design and (iii) minimal requirements of hardware and software for the laboratory (See documents and layout: 2).

INAOE Research Internship in Robotics

Puebla, México Sep 2003 – Mar 2004

with microcontrollers PIC

• I implemented a speed control for a two-degree-of-freedom robot with microcontrollers PIC 16F84 & 16F877 which communicated via RS-232 to LabVIEW's Virtual Instruments.

TEACHING AND SUPERVISION EXPERIENCE

King's College London Supervision

London, UK

Jan 2020 – Present

Student: Thea Bautista

Oct 2021 – May 2022

M. Eng. in Biomedical Eng: GAN-based synthetic ultrasound imaging for fetal development Co-supervisors: H. Kerdegari, L. Peralta-Pereira, and R. Aughwane

Student: Guilherme Gomes de Figueiredo

Jun 2021 – Aug 2021

Summer Project: synthetic ultrasound imagining with AI

Student: Amal Hussein

Jun 2021 – Aug 2021

Summer Project: Ultrasound-guidance simulator

Student: Alexander Mitton

Jan 2020 – Sep 2020

M.Sc. Project: Vibro-tactile stimulator for dystonia research Co-supervisors: C. Bergeles, V. Mcclelland and A. Worley

Student: Alexander Mitton

Jan 2020 - Sep 2020

M.Sc. Project: Vibro-tactile stimulator for dystonia research Co-supervisors: C. Bergeles, V. Mcclelland and A. Worley

Teaching Associate

Jan 2020 – Present

Medical Robotics. Lecturer: Dr. Hongbin Liu

 Medical Robotics. Lecturer: Dr. Christos Bergeles
 Jan 2021 – Apr 2021

 Medical Robotics. Lecturer: Dr. Christos Bergeles

The University of Birmingham Teaching Associate

Birmingham, UK Aug 2014 – Apr 2018

• Engineering Maths 2. Lecturers: Prof. Martin Russell, Dr Carl Anthony	Jan 2018 – Apr2018
• Engineering Maths 2. Lecturer: Prof. Martin Russell	Aug 2017 – Dec 2017
Computing for Engineering. Lecturer: Dr Sridhar Pammu	Aug 2017 – Dec 2017
Matlab Laboratories. Lecturer: Dr Edward Tarte	Jan 2017 – Apr 2017
Computing for Engineering. Lecturer: Dr Sridhar Pammu	Aug 2016 - Dec 2016
• Small Embedded Systems. Lecturer: Prof. Chris Baber	Aug 2016 – Dec 2016

Supervision Jun 2018 – Dec 2018

Student: Dinghuang Zhang

M.Sc. Project: Tools for Human-Humanoid Collaboration

Co-supervisor: Chris Baber.

Bilingual Hight School TECMilenio University Teaching Associate

Puebla, México Aug 2013 – Dec 2013

• Information Technology 🗹, Euclidean Geometry 🖸, and Microsoft Office Access 🖸

Universidad Madero Teaching Associate in Mechatronic Eng.

Puebla, México Jan 2012 – Dec 2012

• Fundamentals of Automation [2], Industrial Electronics [2], Research Projects [2], Metrology [2], Physics [2], and Computer Integrating Manufacturing, and Power Electronics

Universidad Iberoamericana Puebla Teaching Associate in Electronic Eng.

Puebla, México Jan 2007 – Dec 2011

• Stochastic Processes 🗷, Digital Signal Processing 🖸, and Analog Filters.

Instituto Tecnológico Superior de Atlixco Teaching Associate in Mechatronic Eng.

Puebla, México Aug 2006 – Jun 2007

- (01/2007 06/2007) Electronics I, Numerical Methods, and Electricity and Magnetism.
- (08/2006 12/2006) Electricity and Magnetism, and Electricity and Industrial Electronics

PUBLICATIONS

- 1. **M. Xochicale** and C. Baber, "Nonlinear methods to quantify movement variability in human-humanoid interaction activities," Mar. 2021. arXiv: 1810.09249 [eess.SP], Full Manuscript.
- 2. R. Montenegro, E. Corona, D. Badillo-Perez, A. Mandujano, L. Vazquez, D. Cruz, and M. Xochicale, "Air4children: Artificial intelligence and robotics for children," in 16th Annual Conference on Human-Robot Interaction (HRI '21), Feb. 2021. arXiv: 2103.07637 [cs.R0].
- 3. **M. Xochicale** and C. Baber, "Towards the analysis of movement variability in human-humanoid imitation activities," in *5th International Conference on Human Agent Interaction (HAI '17)*, Bielefeld, Germany, Oct. 2017, Poster Paper.
- 4. M. Xochicale, C. Baber, and O. Mourad, "Towards the quantification of human-robot imitation using wearable inertial sensors," in 12th Annual Conference on Human-Robot Interaction (HRI '17), Vienna, Austria, Mar. 2017, Poster Paper.
- 5. **M. Xochicale**, C. Baber, and O. Mourad, "Analysis of the movement variability in dance activities using wearable sensors," in *2nd International Symposium on Wearable Robotics (WeRob '16)*, Segovia, Spain, Oct. 2016, Poster Paper.
- 6. **M. Xochicale**, C. Baber, and O. Mourad, "Understanding movement variability of simplistic gestures using an inertial sensor," in *5th ACM International Symposium on Pervasive Displays* (*PerDis* '16), Oulu, Finland, Jun. 2016, Poster Paper.
- 7. **M. Xochicale** and G. Jovanovic-Dolecek, "A new method for design narrow band lowpass fir filters using a scale function," in *2nd International Conference on Electronic Design (ICED '06)*, Veracruz, Mexico, Nov. 2006, Conference Paper.

POSTERS

- 1. **M. Xochicale**, "Open-cortex: A continuous integration framework for open scientific communication," in 1st Conference on Reproducibility, Replicability and Trust in Science (RRTS '20), Cambridge, England (Virtual Conference), Sep. 2020, Poster Abstract.
- 2. **M. Xochicale**, "Quantification of dynamic facial expressions with shannon entropy in human-humanoid interaction," in *1st Symposium on Machine Learning and Dynamical Systems* (*MLDS* '19), London, UK, Feb. 2019, Poster Abstract.

TALKS

1. **M. Xochicale** and C. Baber, "Nonlinear analysis to quantify human movement variability from time-series data," in *neuromatch* 3.0 (*NMC3 '20*), Virtual Conference, Oct. 2020, Presentation Abstract.

- 2. M. Xochicale, "Quantifying movement variability with nonlinear dynamics for human-humanoid interaction," in 25th International Conference on Difference Equations and Applications (ICDEA '19), London, UK, Jun. 2019, Slices abstract.
- 3. M. Xochicale, "Quantifying the inherent chaos of human movement variability," in 15th Experimental Chaos and Complexity Conference (ECCC '18), Madrid, Spain, Jun. 2018, Presentation Abstract.
- 4. M. Xochicale and C. Baber, "Towards the analysis of movement variability for facial expressions with nonlinear dynamics," in 7th Consortium of European Research on Emotion Conference (CERE '18), Glasgow, Scotland, UK, Apr. 2018, Presentation abstract.

AND HONOURS

- GRANTS, AWARDS King's Public Engagement grant for the project "FETUS: Finding a fETus with an Ultrasound Simulator" led by myself and in collaboration with Fang-Yu Lin and Shu Wang 🗹 (07/01/2021 -07/01/2022)
 - Alexander Mitton won the Outstanding Individual Project award for his M.Sc. project, which I was the main supervisor, on designing a wearable, vibrotactile stimulation device for patients with dystonia 🗹 (15/10/2020)
 - King's Health Partners grant for the project "Sensory system abnormalities in childhood dystonia" lead by Verity McClelland and in collaboration with Carlos Seneci (14/04/2020 -9/06/2020)
 - My work "Towards Healthy Ageing with Humanoid Robots" was selected for a talk at the second forum of Mexican Talent, Innovation Match MX 2017, 🗷 🖺 🛗 11/01/2017
 - I won the best poster award at the XIV Symposium of Mexican Students in the UK at University 16-18/06/2016 of Edinburgh 🗹
 - My project of a low-cost robot was selected among 125 applications received from 35 countries and presented at the first international public entrepreneurship program in Mexico (MECATE 2015). 🗗 🛗 20-24/07/2015
 - Ph.D. scholarship by the Mexican National Council on Science and Technology. 11/2014-11/2018
 - Markovito's team won the first place at the Mexican Tournament of Robotics 2013 in the category at HOME where I presented a Human-Robot Interaction Dance Demo. 25-27/05/2013
 - M.Sc. scholarship by the Mexican National Council on Science and Technology. 09/2004-09/2006

SKILLS

- Programming Python[2014-present], R[2013-present], Robot Operating System (ROS)[2016present], GNU-Octave (or MatLab)[2009-present], LATEX[2006-present], C and C++[2015present], Processing[2012-present], the shell[2010-present], GNU-emacs[2010-present], vim[2016present], pandoc[2017-present], open-source enthusiast at GitHub (@mxochicale)[2015-present], and continuous integration and continuous delivery [2019-present].
- Tools GNU/Linux Operating System user (e.g. OpenSuse, Debian and Ubuntu)[2005-present] Single-board computers and microcontrollers (e.g. NVIDIA Jetson Nano, RaspberryPi, Beagle-Bone, Arduino and PIC)[2010-present], Inertial Measurement Units (e.g. calibration, collection and data analysis)[2013-present], Web design (e.g. Github pages, Jekyll)[2015-present], and Graphic design (e.g. Inkscape, GIMP)[2014-present], CAD design (e.g. Autodesk invetor, blender, FreeCAD)[2015-present], Artificial Neural Networks (e.g. PyTorch, and TensorFlow)[2017present], and 3D printing (e.g., flsun, cura) [2019-present].

Languages Spanish[Native], English[Fluent], Chinese[Beginner]

FXTRA ACTIVITIES

King's College London Outreach activities and scientific engagement

London, UK Sep 2019 – Present

- Organising events in the Early Career Researcher Network of the BMEIS 01-01-2021 present.
- Participation in the Westminster Enterprise Week to engage students aged 14-18 to Biomedical Engineering 10-11-2021
- Participant in the STEAM WEEK organised by the City Westminster Council to engage students aged 14-18 to STEAM ♥ 23-03-2021
- · Alexandra Lautarescu and I organised the Reproducible, Interpretable, Open, & Transparent Science Club at St Thomas' Hospital 02-2020 - 06-2020
- For the event In2ScienceUK, I shared my scientific journey to young scientist on how they can become better scientist. 20-08-2019

• For the New Scientist Live, I showcased software that helps doctors to create 3D models of brain tumors using AI.

09-2019

University of Birmingham Outreach activities and scientific engagement

Birmingham, UK Aug 2014 – Jun 2018

- Finalist at the Three Minute Thesis Competition 2018. Video: and GitHub: 505-2018
- Research Poster Conference for (2015) 🖾, (2016) 🖾, and (2018) 🖾. GitHub: 🖝.
- Demoing Human-Robot Activities at the Undergraduate Open Days. GitHub: . 2014–2018
- Coordinator of the Science Seminars for the Mexican Society. GitHub: , Website: . 2017–2018

AIR4Children México & UK

- Building Artificial Intelligence and Robotics for Children (air4children) with the purpose of teaching AIR to children for free. Twitter: **y**@air4children GitHub: **d**@air4children 2019–Present
- Creation Libre Robotics, a non-profit organization aiming to freely transfer knowledge in Robotics to Mexican children. Website: 2013 2017

Developer of the Website "Machine Learning for México"

México & UK

• GitHub: **⑤**, Website: **②** 2013 – 2018